Inventory of the Oleg Nikolaevich Moskvin papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Oleg Nikolaevich Moskvin papers
1962-1999
2008C68
Moskvin, Oleg Nikolaevich, 1954-
10 ms. boxes, 2 oversize boxes (7.5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The papers are comprised of writings, correspondence, memoranda, government documents, and printed matter relating to civil liberties and independent labor movements in the Soviet Union and post-Soviet Russia.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2008.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Nezavisimost' records, 1989-2001, Hoover Institution Archives
Russian independent trade union publications collection, 1989-1999, Hoover Institution Archives
SMOT (Svobodnoe mezhprofessional'noe ob'edinenie trudiashchikhsia) records, 1988-1998, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical/Historical Note
1954 September 4 Born, Leningrad, Soviet Union
1976 Joined editorial board of the underground journal Demokrat
1976 November 4 Arrested by police for political activity
1977 June 8 Sentenced to psychiatric confinement in Leningrad and Kazan' for "socially dangerous" behavior
1984 March 30 Released from psychiatric confinement
1984 December 3 Began working as a painter at the "Kartonazhnik" factory in Leningrad
1986 July 4 First of repeated firings from "Kartonazhnik" for trade union activities
1988 January 14-February 3 Successful hunger strike for reinstatement at work
1989 June 16 Independent trade union "Nezavisimost'" established
1992 January 16 Final dismissal from "Kartonazhnik"
1992 August 24 Registered as journalist
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, government documents, photographs and printed matter relating to the development of independent labor groups in late-Soviet Leningrad. Comprised primarily of correspondence between Moskvin and various labor organizers and government officials, the papers illustrate the rise of Nezavisimost', one of the first independent trade unions in the Soviet Union.
The bulk of the collection dates from 1986 through 1992, when Moskvin was active in the rapidly developing workers' movement in Leningrad. In 1986, shortly after joining the labor group Rabochaia initsiativa, Moskin sent a series of reports to Pravda criticizing factory management for misuse of property and the unfair awarding of bonuses. These reports, titled "Vzgliad iz khudozhki," can be found in the Writings series. Moskvin was subsequently fired and successfully filed a number of complaints, petitions, and cases for reinstatement. These documents, which can be found in the Court cases file, show the Soviet court system's evolving relationship with trade unions.
In June 1989, Moskvin and other labor organizers formed the independent trade union Nezavisimost', which emphasized workers' control over wages and factory administration. Moskvin founded his own cell within the union, the Tsentr vzaimopomoshchi rabochikh (Center for Workers' Mutual Aid), documents of which can be found in the Labor movement files. The TsVR agitated on behalf of factory workers across Leningrad who had been fired for political activities.
Moskvin's interest in the use of psychiatry as a tool for political repression is reflected in the Subject file, which includes articles and correspondence regarding psychiatric practices in the Soviet Union. The Subject file also documents Soviet and post-Soviet elections in Leningrad and St. Petersburg, particularly through the lens of Gennadiĭ Kravchenko, a Rabochaia initsiativa activist elected to the Leningrad Soviet. Newspapers, correspondence, and electoral flyers reflect the multi-party democratic movement in the city.
Related Article
Temkina, Anna A. "The Workers' Movement in Leningrad, 1986-91." Soviet Studies 44 (1992): 209-236. PURL: www.jstor.org/stable/152023
Arrangement
The collection is organized into seven series: Biographical file, Correspondence, Court cases files, Labor movement documents, Writings, Subject file, and Newspapers
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Labor movement--Soviet Union.; Labor movement--Russia (Federation); Civil rights--Soviet Union.; Dissenters--Soviet Union.
Collection Contents
- Biographical file, 1962-1994
  Contains correspondence, medical reports, notes, photographs, records and sketches, largely relating to Moskvin's hunger strike and psychiatric care. Arranged alphabetically by subject or physical form.
  - Hunger strike, 1986-1988
    - Medical report, 1986-1987 (Folder 1: 1)
    - "O prodolzhenii golodovki i usloviiakh ee prekrashcheniia,", 1988 January 31 (Folder 1: 2)
    - Reports and correspondence, 1987-1988 (Folder 1: 3)
    - "Vzgliad zainteresovannogo postoronnego," Vecherniĭ Leningrad, 1988 February 11 (Folder 1: 4)
      Article on Moskvin's hunger strike and letter in response
  - "Istoriia bolezni,", 1977-1993 (Folder 1: 5-6)
  - Journalism career, 1992-1994
    - 1992 July-August (Folder 1: 7)
      Correspondence and notes. Includes registration as a correspondent for Kontrargumenty i fakty
    - 1993-1994 (Folder 1: 8)
    - Kontrargumenty i fakty, 1992 September 10
  - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Folder 1: 10-16)
    Handwritten and in the original order
  - Napravlenie na VTEK, 1988 April 15 and undated (Folder 1: 17)
    Reports, correspondence and forms relating to Moskvin's medical condition
  - Notebooks, 1986-1987 and undated (Folder 1: 18-19)
  - Passport photographs, 1976, 1994 and undated (Folder 1: 20)
    Photocopies
  - Pension, 1986-1989 (Folder 1: 21)
    Correspondence and forms
  - Posters, undated (Folder 11: 6)
    Two posters designed by Moskvin, one relating to the Komsomol and the other to the Russian Museum
  - Psychiatric records, 1986-1992 (Folder 1: 22)
    Includes medical records, notes and correspondence
  - Rehabilitation document, 1992 April 17 (Folder 1: 23)
  - Salary reports, correspondence and forms, 1985-1992
    - 1985-1988 (Folder 1: 24-26)
    - 1991-1992 (Folder 2: 1-2)
    - Litsevoĭ schet, 1985-1988
      - 1985-1987 (Folder 11: 7)
      - 1988 (Folder 2: 3)
  - School notebooks, circa 1962 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Sketches and drawings, undated (Folder 2: 5)
  - Stamp, cover of the journal "Demokrat,", undated (Folder 2: 6)
  - Teaching career, 1993 (Folder 2: 7)
    Includes class roster, correspondence and sketches
  - Work injury, 1986-1989
    - Correspondence and reports, 1986-1989 (Folder 2: 8)
    - "O neschastnom sluchae na proizvodstve,", 1986 June 13 (Folder 2: 9)
- Correspondence, 1978-1994
  Contains letters, reports, and receipts, primarily relating to Moskvin's tenure at the Kartonazhnik factory. Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Chelovek i zakon, 1989 (Folder 2: 10)
  - Chelpanova, Liudmila Danilovna, General Director of the Kartonazhnik factory, 1986-1993
    - 1986-1991 (Folder 2: 11-15)
    - 1993 (Folder 2: 16)
  - Fedorov, A.P., 1987 July 10 (Folder 2: 17)
  - Glashataĭ, numbered letters to the editor, circa 1993 (Folder 2: 18-23)
  - Komissiia po trudovym sporam P.O. Kartonazhnik, 1986 (Folder 2: 24)
  - Kravchenko, Genadii, 1991-1994 (Folder 2: 25-26, Folder 3: 1-8)
    Correspondence relating to Moskvin's work history, medical diagnosis and rehabilitation
  - Lebedev, Aleksandr Vasil'evich, 1989-1991 (Folder 3: 9)
  - Leningradskiĭ gorodskoĭ sud, 1989-1990 (Folder 3: 10-11)
  - Medical correspondence, 1983-1992 (Folder 3: 12)
  - Ministerstvo finansov RSFSR, 1989 January 3 (Folder 3: 13)
  - Ministerstvo sviazi RSFSR, 1987 April 24 (Folder 3: 14)
  - Moskvin family, 1978-1981 (Folder 3: 15-20)
  - Moskvin, Nikolai, 1986-1989 and undated (Folder 4: 1-13)
  - Sekretariat zamestitelia predsedatelia, 1989 May 19 (Folder 4: 14)
  - Slobodeniuk, E.P., 1990 October 25 and undated (Folder 4: 15)
  - Timofeeva, G.S., 1986 July (Folder 4: 16)
    Dismissal letter from the Kartonazhnik factory
  - TSentral'naia gorodskaia vrachebnego-trudovaia ekspertnaia kommissiia (VTEK), Leningrad, 1989 May-September (Folder 4: 17)
  - Unattributed, 1986-1994 and undated (Folder 4: 18-20)
  - Upravlenie mestnoĭ promyshlennosti, Leningrad, 1987 October 30 (Folder 4: 21)
  - Upravlenie organizatsii truda i zarabotnoĭ platy, 1987 November 23 and December 23 (Folder 4: 22)
  - Vedeneev, A.F., 1989 July-August (Folder 4: 23)
  - Verkhovnyĭ sud RSFSR, 1990 March 12 (Folder 4: 24)
  - Zverev, S.S., 1986 January-July (Folder 4: 25)
  - Miscellaneous envelopes and receipts, circa 1986 (Folder 4: 26)
- Court Cases file, 1986-1995
  Consists of correspondence, reports, notes, and court records relating to Moskvin's repeated dismissals and reinstatements at the Kartonazhnik factory. Arranged in two groups: chronological and alphabetical.
  - 1986-1987 (Folder 4: 27-30)
  - 1988 (Folder 4: 31, Folder 5: 1)
  - 1989-1995 (Folder 5: 2-26)
  - Notebook, 1987-1990 (Folder 6: 1)
  - Notes, undated (Folder 6: 2-4)
  - "Protest v Prezidium Sankt-Peterburgskogo gorodskogo suda,", 1992 August 24 (Folder 6: 5)
  - Reprimand, Kartonazhnik factory, 1986-1990 (Folder 6: 6)
    Reports, correspondence and court files related to Moskvin's reprimand and salary reduction at the Kartonazhnik factory
  - Slander case, 1987 (Folder 6: 7)
- Labor movement documents, 1985-1994
  Contains notes, reports, correspondence, circulated material, clippings, petitions, published matter, signs, transparencies, telephone directories and questionnaires relating to workers' movements in Leningrad and St. Petersburg. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Demidovich, Tat'iana Ivanovna, 1990-1993 and undated
    Correspondence, reports and notes relating to her dismissal and reinstatement at the Zvezda factory
    - 1990-1993 (Folder 6: 8-13)
    - Assorted, undated (Folder 6: 14)
      Includes two clippings
  - Demokratizatsiia profsoiuzov, 1988-1989 (Folder 6: 15-17)
    Notes, reports, correspondence and circulated material, 1988 and undated
  - "Informatsiia k razmyshleniiu. O klassovom terrore,", undated (Folder 6: 18)
  - "Kak khotiat pobedit' Leninizm," N.K. Vodomerov, Vologodskiĭ politicheskiĭ institut, 1985 (Folder 6: 19)
  - Kartonazhnik factory, 1985-1992
    - Awards and incentives, 1988-1990 (Folder 6: 20)
    - Correspondence, 1987-1992 (Folder 6: 21-25)
    - Petition, circa 1991 November (Folder 6: 26)
    - Polozhenie o provedenii vyborov rukovoditeleĭ na PO 'Kartonazhnik', 1988 February 25-June 13 (Folder 6: 27)
      Also includes reports and correspondence relating to factory elections
    - Posters, undated (Folder 11: 3)
      Shows correspondence between Moskvin, Chelpanova and others
    - Protocols, 1987 March-May (Folder 6: 28)
    - Strike, 1988 January-February (Folder 6: 29)
    - Workers' accounts, 1985-1988 and undated (Folder 7: 1-2)
      Typescripts and manuscripts of testimonials from Kartonazhnik factory workers on their experiences with factory administration
    - Workers' collective, 1987 September 21 - 1988 December 7 (Folder 7: 3)
      Reports, petitions and clippings
  - Kasatkin, Viktor Anatol'evich, 1989-1990
    - Clippings, 1990 September-October
      - "Eshche o golodovke," Leninskoe znamia, 1990 September 19 (Folder 7: 4)
      - "Miagkoe reshenie," Vecherniĭ Leningrad, 1990 November 30 (Folder 7: 5)
      - "Moda na golodovku?" Edinstvo, no. 14, 1990 August 20-27 (Folder 7: 6)
      - "Solidarité avec Victor Kassatkine," Informations Ouvrieres, no. 1485, 1990 September 12 (Folder 7: 7)
      - "Za opytom - v Tosno," Leninskoe znamia, 1990 August 9 (Folder 7: 8)
    - Correspondence, 1990-1992
      - Assorted official, 1990-1991 and undated (Folder 7: 9)
      - Kravchenko, Gennadiĭ, 1990-1991 (Folder 7: 10)
      - Le comité international contre la Répression, 1990 September 21 (Folder 7: 11)
      - Leningradskiĭ gorodskoĭ Sovet, 1990-1991 (Folder 7: 12)
      - Severo-zapadnaia transportnaia prokuratura, 1991-1992 (Folder 7: 13)
      - Svobodnoe Mezhprofessional'noe Ob"edinenie Trudiashchikhsia (SMOT), circa 1990 (Folder 7: 14)
      - TsVR-Nezavisimost', 1990-1991 and undated (Folder 7: 15-17)
    - "Dogovor o vzaimnykh obiazatel'stvakh administratsii i rabochikh,", circa 1990 (Folder 7: 18)
    - Notes, circa 1990 (Folder 7: 19)
    - Notebooks, undated (Folder 7: 20)
    - "Platforma Kasatkina,", 1989 (Folder 7: 21)
    - "Pochemu ob"iavil golodovku Kasatkin?", circa 1990 (Folder 7: 22)
    - Protocols, 1990 August and 1991 May (Folder 7: 23)
    - Reports and statements, 1990 (Folder 7: 24)
    - Signs, circa 1989 (Folder 7: 25)
      Posters and flyers relating to Kasatkin's hunger strike
  - Kravchenko, Genadii, 1989-1993
    - Clippings, 1991-1992 (Folder 7: 26)
    - Correspondence, 1991-1993 (Folder 7: 27-29)
    - General, 1991 (Folder 7: 30)
      Includes reports, correspondence and notes
    - O konstitutsionnom Sude RSFSR, 1991 July 12 (Folder 7: 31)
    - O statuse narodnogo deputata mestnogo Soveta narodnykh deputatov RSFSR," Postanovlenie Verkhovnogo Soveta RSFSR, 1990 October 30 (Folder 7: 32)
    - O vnesenii izmeneniĭ i dopolneniĭ v kodeks zakonov o trude RSFSR, 1992 September 25 (Folder 8: 1)
    - Research materials, 1991-1993 (Folder 8: 2)
    - Speech, Profsiouznaia konferenziia, 1989 October 14 (Folder 8: 3)
    - Stenogramma 8-i sessii Lensoveta za 14.05.91 g., 1991 May 14 (Folder 8: 4)
    - Telephone directories, 1991 March and undated (Folder 8: 5)
    - Transcript, Sankt-Peterburgskiĭ gorodskoĭ sovet, circa 1992 (Folder 8: 6)
      Includes a discussion of strikes and the organization Nezavisimost'
    - Working files, 1975, 1991-1992 and undated (Folder 8: 7-9)
    - Writings, 1991 (Folder 8: 10)
      Includes "Obrashcheniia k rabochim i demokraticheskim deputatam Lensoveta"
    - Marksistko-Leninskoe uchenie o gosudarstve, T. Khabarova, 1994 June 6 (Folder 8: 11)
    - Miscellaneous flyers and brochures, 1989-1998 (Folder 8: 12)
    - Perestroĭka, 1987
      - Clippings, 1987 (Folder 8: 13)
      - General, 1987 (Folder 8: 14)
        Includes organizational files, correspondence and reports relating to the "Zashchita aktivistov" section of Perestroĭka
      - Notes and minutes, 1987 (Folder 8: 15)
        Minutes show participation of Anatoliĭ Chubaĭs
    - Prisatka, Marina, 1987-1988
      - Clippings, 1988 (Folder 8: 16)
      - Reports and correspondence, 1987-1988 (Folder 8: 17)
        Relates to the firing and appeal of factory worker Prisatka
    - Rabochaia initsiativa, 1988-1993 and undated
      - General, 1992-1993 and undated (Folder 8: 18)
        Reports, clippings, circulated material, sketches and a telegram. Includes history of the group written by Moskvin
      - Petitions, 1988-1991 (Folder 8: 19)
      - "Politicheskiĭ kommentarii kluba 'Rabochaia initsiativa' k poboishchu v Moskve,", circa 1993 (Folder 8: 20)
    - Rabochiĭ sud, 1990-1991 (Folder 8: 21)
      Files relating to the project founded by Moskvin within the TSentr vzaimopomoshchi rabochikh profsoiuza Nezavisimost'
    - Tikhonovich, D.A., 1987-1989 (Folder 8: 22)
      Correspondence and reports relating to dismissal from the Kartonazhnik factory
    - TSentr vzaimopomoshchi rabochikh profsoiuza Nezavisimost' (TsVR-Nezavisimost'), 1989-1991 and undated
      - Address lists, undated (Folder 8: 23)
      - Budget, 1989 November-1990 April (Folder 8: 24)
        Ledger with notes
      - "Chto nuzhno rabochemu klassu?", circa 1990 (Folder 8: 25)
      - Circulated material, 1989-1990 and undated (Folder 8: 26)
      - Clippings, 1989-1991 (Folder 8: 27)
      - Contracts, 1989-1990 (Folder 8: 28)
      - Correspondence, 1989-1990 and undated (Folder 8: 29-30)
      - Flyers, 1990 (Folder 8: 31)
      - "Kak sozdat' profsoiuz 'Nezavisimost' na predpriiatii,", 1989 (Folder 8: 32)
      - Meeting, 1990 March 15 (Folder 8: 33)
      - Notebook, undated (Folder 9: 1)
      - Notes, circa 1990 (Folder 9: 2)
      - Obshchee delo budget, 1990 September-1993 June (Folder 9: 3)
      - Petition, correspondence and circulated materials, 1991 November-December (Folder 9: 4)
      - "Politekonomicheskaia doktrina demokraticheskogo rabochego dvizheniia na sovremennom etape,", 1989 April 19 (Folder 9: 5)
      - Posters, 1990 August 26 and undated (Folder 11: 5)
        One poster relates to Viktor Kasatkin
      - Printing transparencies, 1989 October-1990 February (Folder 9: 6)
        Flyers relating to workers' rights and a miners' strike
      - Proclamations, 1989 (Folder 9: 7)
      - Questionnaire, circa 1990 (Folder 9: 8)
        Moskvin's responses to questions about Nezavisimost'
      - "Trebovaniia No. 1,", 1991 December 24 (Folder 9: 9)
        Also includes correspondence and notes related to workers' demands
      - "Ustav professional'noĭ assotsiatsii rabochikh Nezavisimost', 1990 (Folder 9: 10)
      - Working files, 1989-1990 (Folder 9: 11)
- Writings, 1986-1993
  Consists of manuscripts, typescripts, clippings, published matter and correspondence. Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - "Obman: po motivam narodnoĭ iaponskoĭ pritchi,", undated (Folder 9: 12)
    Handwritten draft with corrections
  - "Obman,", undated (Folder 9: 13)
    Typescript with corrections
  - Political writings, undated (Folder 9: 14)
    Three short pieces
  - Published articles, 1993 and undated (Folder 9: 15)
    Two clippings of articles "S dorogi - v tupik" and "Rabochaia initsiativa"
  - Publisher correspondence, 1990 and 1993
    - Pravda, 1993 (Folder 9: 16)
    - Sever and Zvezda, 1990 (Folder 9: 17)
      Relates to publishing Obman
  - Screenplay fragment, undated (Folder 9: 18)
  - "Sud'ba pisatelia v soiuze,", undated (Folder 9: 19)
  - Vstuplenie v mir, undated (Folder 9: 20)
  - "Vzgliad iz khudozhki,", 1986 May-1987 May (Folder 9: 21)
    Consists of four essays sent to Pravda
  - "Zamechaniia tekhnicheskogo poriadka,", 1991 June 15 (Folder 9: 22)
- Subject file, 1964-1996
  Contains photographs, circulated materials, clippings, correspondence, reports, applications and forms, largely relating to elections in Leningrad and St. Petersburg. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Armenia photographs, 1988
    - July 5 (Folder 9: 23)
    - Erevan, 1988 August (Folder 9: 24)
      Protests and tanks on Ploshchad' Lenina
    - Erevan, 1988 September (Folder 9: 25-26)
    - Erevan, 1988 October (Folder 9: 27)
    - Political posters, 1988 (Folder 9: 28)
      Photographs of posters in Russian and Armenian
    - Stepanakert, 1988 February and August (Folder 9: 29)
  - Assotsiatsiia zhertv prestuplenii, 1991-1993 (Folder 9: 30)
    Correspondence and meeting minutes
  - Elections, Leningrad and St. Petersburg, 1989-1996
    - Ballots, candidate rosters and notes, 1990-1993 (Folder 9: 31)
    - Candidate flyers, 1990-1996 and undated (Folder 9: 32-36)
    - Nikolai Moskvin candidate flyers and notes, 1990 (Folder 9: 37)
  - "Golodanie radi zdorov'ia," Moscow, 1973 (Folder 9: 38)
  - Housing construction in St. Petersburg, circa 1992 (Folder 9: 39)
  - Kas-Kor, Informatsionnyĭ tsentr rabechego dvizheniia, 1990 June 1 (Folder 11: 4)
  - Kuzin Group International, 1991 June 24 (Folder 9: 40)
    Agreement between the Leningrad city soviet and the Kuzin Group
  - Leningradskiĭ Dom mira i miloserdiia, 1990 November 14 (Folder 10: 1)
  - 'Lennord,', 1990 February 12 (Folder 10: 2)
  - Manakov, N.N., 1987-1989
    - Fruzenskoĭ raĭonnyĭ narodnyĭ sud, 1987-1989 (Folder 10: 3)
    - "Khodit zhaloba po krugu,", 1988 March 29 (Folder 10: 4)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1987 (Folder 10: 5)
      Includes complaints by Moskvin
    - Prokurata g. Leningrada, 1987-1988 (Folder 10: 6)
  - Opposition groups, 1993 March 17 and undated
    - Meeting report, 1993 March 17 (Folder 10: 7)
    - Narodnyĭ Front banner, undated (Folder 11: 1)
  - Partiia vozrozhdeniia, October 1991 (Folder 10: 8)
    Conference program
  - Privatization, 1991-1992
    - "O privatizatsii gosudarstvennykh i munitsipal'nykh predpriiatii v RSFSR,", 1991 July 3 (Folder 10: 9)
    - "O programme privatizatsii gosudarstvennykh i munitsipal'nykh predpriiatii v Sankt-Peterburge na 1992 god," Malyĭ Sovet, Sankt-Peterburgskiĭ gorodskoĭ sovet narodnykh deputatov, 1992 February 25 (Folder 10: 10)
  - Psychiatry, 1964-1993
    - Clippings, 1987-1993 (Folder 10: 11, Folder 11: 2)
      Items relating to psychiatry in the Soviet Union
    - "O narusheniiakh zakonnosti v TMO 'Psikhiatriia',", circa 1992 (Folder 10: 12)
    - "Polozhenie o lechebno-proizvodstvennykh masterskikh pri psikhonevrologicheskikh i psikhiatricheskikh uchrezhdeniiakh,", 1964 (Folder 10: 13)
    - Report, speech, notes and correspondence, 1990-1992 (Folder 10: 14)
      Documents relating to psychiatry in the Soviet Union and Moskvin's diagnosis
  - Ro, Iakov Khristianovich, 1991-1996 (Folder 10: 15)
    Correspondence, clippings and writings relating to the World War II veteran
  - Russko-germanskaia assotsiatsiia po propagande klassicheskogo kul'turnogo naslediia, 1991-1994
    - Conference program, correspondence, proposal and report, 1993-1994 (Folder 10: 16)
      Organization also known as the Russisch-Deutsche Assoziation für die Verbreitung klassischen Kulturgutes
    - Correspondence and writings, 1991-1992 and undated (Folder 10: 17)
  - Russkaia tserkov' Moskovskogo raĭona g. Leningrada, 1989 September-1992 February (Folder 10: 18)
    Application and correspondence
  - Svobodnaia Rossiia, 1988 and undated (Folder 10: 19)
    Also includes materials relating to the organization "Pamiat'"
  - Tourism, 1991-1992 (Folder 10: 20)
    Correspondence, clippings and petitions relating to tourism collectives in Leningrad and St. Petersburg
  - Vsesoiuznaia gosudarstvennaia teleradiokompaniia, circa 1991 (Folder 10: 21)
    Two petitions
  - Vsesoiuznoe obshchestvo 'Optimalist,', undated (Folder 10: 22)
  - Workers' collectives, early 1990s (Folder 10: 23)
    Includes presidential decrees, forms and a clipping
- Newspapers, 1988-1999
  Contains incomplete runs of Soviet and post-Soviet newspapers primarily from Leningrad and St. Petersburg. Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Allo, no. 5(11), 1992 (Folder 10: 24)
  - Andropovskaia pravda, no. 2(12), 1993 (Folder 12: 1)
  - Argumenty i kontrargumenty, 1994-1996 (Folder 12: 1)
  - Bumbarash-2017: gazeta rossiĭskogo kommunisticheskogo soiuza molodezhi, 1995-1996 (Folder 12: 1)
  - Chto delat', no. 9(32), 1996 (Folder 12: 1)
  - Duel', nos. 30(121) and 37(128), 1999 (Folder 11: 8)
  - Edinstvo, no. 13, 1990 (Folder 11: 8)
  - Fontanka, 1994 January 26 (Folder 11: 8)
  - Giperboreia, 1992 August-September (Folder 12: 2)
  - Glashataĭ, no. 2(41), 1993 (Folder 11: 8)
  - IRA-Ekspress, no. 22, 1992 (Folder 10: 25)
  - Izvestiia, 1989 April 16 (Folder 11: 8)
  - Kommentator, no. 16, 1993 (Folder 10: 26)
  - Kommunist Leningrada, no. 3(8), 1994 (Folder 12: 2)
  - Kontrargumenty i fakti, 1992-1994 (Folder 12: 2-3)
  - Leningradskaia pravda, 1988 December 25-1990 March 10 (Folder 11: 9)
  - Molniia, no. 67, 1994 (Folder 12: 3)
  - Nevskoe vremia, no. 138, 1991 (Folder 11: 9)